Harold Van Doren Papers
Harold Van Doren Papers
1952-1956
Van Doren, Harold.
0.25 linear ft.
American industrial designer, design teacher and author. Collection includes photographs, sketches, diagrams, blueprints and drawings.
3181639
Biographical History
Harold Van Doren (1895-1957) was an influential American industrial designer who created numerous iconic streamlined design items including toys, radios, fans, and more. He also taught design and wrote several books on the subject.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Harold Van Doren Papers consists of photographs, sketches (some colored), diagrams, and drawings for various projects, primarily air conditioners and kitchen ranges (ovens). All original folder titles have been preserved, apart from the addition of [19] to normalize the year and the "Miscellaneous" material folder at the end, which contains previously unfoldered material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by folder title. Original folder titles (though not original order of folders) were preserved and used.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of industrial designers; please see for a complete listing of collections.
Subject and Genre Headings
Industrial Design; Van Doren, Harold.; Air conditioning -- Equipment and supplies -- Design and construction.; Industrial design -- United States.; Industrial designers -- United States.; Stoves -- Design and construction.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Drawings (visual works); Photographs.; Sketches.; Industrial designers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harold Van Doren, 1965, 1969.
Inventory
- Project files
  - [19]54 air conditioners, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - [19]54 ranges, 1952 (Box 1)
  - [19]55 air conditioner, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955 ranges, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - [19]55 ranges, built-in, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1955 Windowlette, 1954 (Box 1)
  - [19]56 air conditioner details, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - [19]56 air conditioner sketches, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 ranges sketches, undated (Box 1)
  - Air conditioner "Futures", 1952-1955 (Box 1)
  - Air conditioner grill studies, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Portable air conditioner, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Schick shaver, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Yorkaire unit, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - [Miscellaneous], undated; suitcase, blender[?], vending machines (Box 1)